Guide to the William J. Baumol Papers, 1928-2013 and undated RL.00092
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Writings, 1946-2012 and undated
  - Books, 1951-2010 and undated; 2
    - Productivity Book, 1994; 6 document files; less than 1 MB. (Digital-materials RL00092-SET-0001, Disk RL00092-FL3-0004)
    - Productivity Book - Image Files, 1988-1989; 61 document (Lotus 1-2-3 format) and still image (HP Vector Graphic format) files; less than 1 MB. (Digital-materials RL00092-SET-0001, Disk RL00092-FL5-0088)
    - Productivity Book - Image Files, 1988-1989; 31 document (Lotus 1-2-3 format) and still image (HP Vector Graphic format) files; less than 1 MB. (Digital-materials RL00092-SET-0001, Disk RL00092-FL5-0089)
    - Productivity Book with McLennan, 1985 (Box 5)
      Includes draft materials and related correspondence
    - Productivity Feedback, 1994 (Box 1)
      Draft chapters for book co-authored with Edward Wolff
    - Productivity Feedback, 1994; 3 folders (Box 17)
      Draft chapters and research materials
    - Productivity Feedback, undated (Box 29)
      Includes notes and draft materials
    - Publishing Contracts, 1978; 2006 (Box 23)
    - Superfairness, 1986 (Box 59)
      MIT Press
    - Superfairness Book, Original Artwork, Undated (Box 2)
    - Theory of Environmental Policy, 1984-1986 (Box 3)
    - Volume on Entrepreneurship, 1990 (Box 59)
    - Welfare Economics and the Theory of the State, 1985 (Box 23)
      Includes agreement for new edition of the book
    - Welfare Economics and the Theory of the State (Chinese Translation), 2007 (Box 23)
    - Welfare Economics Book, 2000-2001; 2 folders (Box 14)
    - Welfare Reader, 1996 (Box 59)
    - Welfare Reader, 2001 (Box 36)
    - Wheatsheaf Books, 1985-1986 (Box 14)
      Includes files and correspondence related to publishing a compendium of Baumol's writings
  - Comments and Reviews, 1947-2005; 3
    Contains documents for Baumol's activities as a referee for many academic journals and publishers, as well as published comments and reviews of academic work.
    - A New Critique of Marx's Economics, Review of Morishima, 1975 (Box 45)
    - Articles reviewed or read, 1983-1987; 3 folders (Box 12)
      Includes referee reports and comments and reviews on papers, proposals, and books
    - Book Reviews, 1947-1956 (Box 45)
      Includes drafts and reprints of various book reviews by Baumol
    - Books reviewed, 1979-1989 (Box 15)
    - Bradford DeLong, 1987 (Box 14)
    - Comments, Undated (Box 29)
      Submitted manuscript with editor comments
    - Comments etc. on JPE, 1990 (Box 12)
    - Comments on Contestability, 1982-1986 (Box 13)
      Includes comments received on Baumol's work on contestable markets
    - Journal of Economic Literature, 1986 (Box 14)
    - Journal of Political Economy, 1974-1984; 3 folders (Box 14)
      Includes files related to book reviews
    - Journal Referee Reports, 1975-1983 (Box 23)
    - Letters of Review and Comment, 1988-1989 (Box 12)
      Includes letters commenting on or reviewing writings by others
    - Markets from Networks, H. C. White, 2002 (Box 37)
    - Out of Equilibrium, 2000 (Box 26)
    - Review of An evolutionary theory of economic change by Nelson and Winter, 1983 (Box 51)
    - Review of Baumol's work, 1992 (Box 11)
    - Review of Feldstein, The economics of art museums, 1991-1992 (Box 13)
    - Review of Introduction au Capital de Karl Marx by Maarek, 1977 (Box 51)
    - Review of John R. Hicks: The Economist's Economist by Hamouda, 1993 (Box 1)
    - Review of Lichtenberg, Corporate Takeovers and Productivity, 1991 (Box 13)
    - Review of Lionel Robbins by O'Briend, 1990 (Box 51)
    - Review of Maddison, Phases of Capitalist Development, 1986 (Box 13)
    - Review of Malthus, undated (Box 51)
    - Review of Nau, The Myth of America's Decline: Leading the World Economy into the 1990s, 1991 (Box 13)
    - Review of O'Brien, Lionel Robbins, 1989 (Box 13)
    - Review of Out of Equilibrium, 2000 (Box 51)
    - Review of Routledge book "Hollywood Economics", 2003 (Box 51)
      Related correspondence
    - Review of Stigler Memoirs, Memoirs of an Unregulated Economist, 1989 (Box 13)
    - Review of Studies in Linear and Non-Linear Programming by Arrow, Hurwicz, and Uzawa, 1959 (Box 51)
    - Review of The Cultural Cold War: The CIA and the World of Arts and Letters, 2001 (Box 51)
    - Review of The Making of Harrod's Dynamics, 2000 (Box 51)
    - Review of The Theory of Inter-Sectoral Money Flows and Income Formation by John Chipman, 1952 (Box 51)
    - Review of Theoretical Welfare Economics by J. de V. Graaff, undated (Box 51)
    - Review of Theories of Economic Growth and Development by Irma Adelman, undated (Box 51)
    - Review of Tyler Cowen "Creative Destruction: How Globalization is Changing the World's Cultures", 2003 (Box 51)
    - Review of Welfare and Competition by Scitovsky, 1971 (Box 51)
    - Review of Williamson, Economic Institutions of Capitalism, 1985 (Box 13)
    - Reviews and Comments, 1983-1984 (Box 2)
      Includes files for reviews and referee activity
    - Reviews and Comments, 1974 (Box 11)
    - Reviews and Comments, 1981-1982; 2 folders (Box 11)
    - Reviews and Comments, 1985 (Box 11)
    - Reviews and Comments, 1986-1987; 3 folders (Box 11)
    - Reviews and Comments, 1979-1995; 15 folders (Box 12)
    - Reviews and Comments, 2000-2005; 5 folders (Box 23)
      Includes referee reports for various outlets
    - Reviews and Comments, 1991-2005; 3 folders (Box 36)
    - Reviews and Comments, 1983-1986; 13 text files; less than 1 MB. (Digital-materials RL00092-SET-0002, Disk RL00092-FL5-0107)
    - Reviews and Comments Correspondence, 1996 (Box 52)
      Drafts of reviews and related correspondence
    - Reviews of Baumol's Books, 1989-2004; 2 folders (Box 52)
      Includes copies of reviews of books by Baumol
    - Reviews of Kaldor, 1961 (Box 52)
    - Reviews of Productivity and American Leadership, 1989-2000; 2 folders (Box 24)
      Includes copies of coverage and reviews of Productivity and American Leadership book co-authored with Sue Ann Batey Blackman and Edward Wolff
    - Reviews-articles, 1989; 2 folders (Box 15)
    - Science Article Comments, 1989 (Box 14)
      Includes comment on "Is there a US Productivity Crisis"
    - Technical Progress, 1991 (Box 14)
    - The Cultural Cold War, 2001 (Box 26)
    - Unlabeled Comments and Reviews, 1993 (Box 29)
      Includes unlabeled reviews and comments on others' written work
- Academia, 1952-2012 and undated
  Includes teaching materials, committee, departmental, and other work for Baumol's professorships at Princeton University and New York University.
  - Teaching, 1978-2010 and undated; 2
    Includes syllabi, lecture notes, sample assignments, and other materials for courses Baumol taught at Princeton and New York University.
    - Class Notes, undated (Box 10)
      Includes unlabeled class notes
    - Description and Analysis of the Price System, 1989 (Box 10)
      Includes teaching materials and exams
    - Econ 102: Microeconomics, 1989-1990; undated; 3 folders (Box 10)
      Includes lecture notes and other teaching materials for course on microeconomics
    - Econ 506: History of Economic Thought, 1978-1979; 13 folders (Box 10)
      Lecture notes on Cournot and Marx, including extensive converage of Marx's theory of value and Baumol's views on the transformation problem
    - Econ 506: History of Economic Thought, 1968-1990; undated; 16 folders (Box 20)
      Syllabi, book orders, course readings, lecture notes on Ricardo, Malthus, and Smith, includes materials on Samuelson's interpretation of Ricardo
    - Econ 541: Industrial Organization and Public Policy, 1980-1986; 2 folders (Box 20)
      Includes lecture notes and other course materials
    - Economic Dynamics and Welfare Theory, 1946-1949 (Box 20)
    - Economics of Antitrust, 1978 (Box 20)
      Includes course readings
    - Economists Calendar, 2010 (Box 20)
    - Entrepreneurship Lecture Notes, 1988 (Box 20)
    - Exams, 1950-1989; 5 folders (Box 20)
      Includes copies of exams for various courses taught by Baumol
    - Health Cost, 2003 (Box 20)
      Includes lecture materials
    - History of Economic Thought, 1979-1988; undated; 3 folders (Box 20)
      Includes lecture notes and course readings
    - Industrial Organization, 1983; undated; 3 folders (Box 20)
      Includes syllabi, lecture notes, and course readings
    - Innovation and Entrepreneurship, 2010-2011; 3 folders (Box 19)
      Includes lecture materials and course readings
    - Lecture Notes, 1978-1979; undated; 6 folders (Box 19)
      Includes lecture notes on Cournot, Marx, Ricardo, Smith, and other topics
    - Lecture Notes, 1989; 10 text files; less than 1 MB. (Digital-materials RL00092-SET-0001, Disk RL00092-FL5-0036)
    - Long-Run Data Transparencies, 1982 (Box 19)
      Includes teaching materials on long-run productivity and growth trends
    - Mathematics for Economists, 1982-1993; 4 folders (Box 19)
    - Mechanisms of Technology Transfer, undated (Box 19)
    - Microeconomics, 1990-2010; 10 folders (Box 19)
      Includes syllabi, lecture notes, course readings, and other related materials
    - Microeconomics assignments and answers, 1994; 6 document files; less than 1 MB. (Digital-materials RL00092-SET-0001, Disk RL00092-FL5-0004)
    - Miscellaneous Lecture Notes, 1965; undated; 3 folders (Box 40)
      Includes unlabeled lecture notes
    - Outline for a one-semester course, undated (Box 40)
    - Principles, 1992-2006; 4 folders (Box 40)
      Includes syllabi, assignments, lecture notes, readings, and other course materials
    - Privatization and Regulation of telephones, undated (Box 40)
    - Reading Lists, 1964-1967 (Box 40)
      Includes reading lists for various courses at Princeton
    - Regulation Lecture Notes, 1983-1994; 3 folders (Box 40)
      Includes lecture notes on economic regulation
    - Research and Writing, 1999; undated; 3 folders (Box 40)
      Includes lecture notes, readings, and other course material for class on the research and writing process to prepare papers for peer review
    - Robbins: English Classical Economists, undated (Box 40)
      Includes copies of lecture notes
    - Sculpture Class, 1981 (Box 40)
    - Statistics, Mozart graphs, undated (Box 40)
      Includes printouts of graphs
    - Talks, undated (Box 40)
      Includes lecture materials for various talks
    - Topics in the microeconomics of regulation, 1994 (Box 40)
    - Transparencies, undated (Box 40)
      Includes various charts and graphs used for lectures
    - US Leadership, undated (Box 40)
    - US Productivity, undated (Box 40)
    - Various Lectures, undated; 2 folders (Box 40)
  - Other Academic Business, 1952-2012; 1
    Contains documents for committee service, departmental duties, and other university service for Baumol's time at both Princeton and New York University.
    - New York University (NYU), 1977-1979 (Box 31)
      Includes files for routine academic business
    - NYU: Berkley Center, 2005-2006 (Box 31)
      Includes files related to programming and events at NYU's Berkley Center for Entreprenuerial Studies and Baumol's role as Academic Director
    - NYU: Bibliography, 1965-1983; 2 folders (Box 31)
      Includes annual faculty activity reports
    - NYU: C.V. Starr Center, 1984-2000; 5 folders (Box 31)
      Includes files for the center research activities, project proposals, and steering committee business for the CV Starr Center at NYU
    - NYU: Carolyn Riportella, 1979 (Box 31)
      Includes files related to Riportella's work as support staff for Baumol
    - NYU: Computer Furniture, 1984-1988 (Box 31)
      Includes files related to purchase of office equipment
    - NYU: Department Items, 1979-1991; 3 folders (Box 31)
      Includes files for routine department business
    - NYU: Draft Material for Department Brochure, 1997 (Box 31)
      Draft materials for Economics Department brochure for students
    - NYU: Education for Entrepreneurship Project, 2004 (Box 31)
      Materials for project funded by Kauffman Foundation
    - NYU: Files on Faculty Achievements, 1983-1986; 12 text files; less than 1 MB. (Digital-materials RL00092-SET-0001, Disk RL00092-FL5-0113)
    - NYU: Forms, 1974-1976; 2 folders (Box 31)
      Forms for routine business at NYU
    - NYU: Grants, 1977-1984 (Box 31)
      Includes files for various grant-funded projects
    - NYU: Harvard University Visiting Committee, 1999 (Box 31)
      Includes materials for serving as external reviewer
    - NYU: Humanities Council, 1982-1984; 2 folders (Box 31)
      Includes files for Baumol's service on the committee
    - NYU: Information, 2003-2004 (Box 31)
      Includes routine informational pamphlets for NYU student and faculty services
    - NYU: Microeconomics Research Fund, 1977-1982; 2 folders (Box 31)
      Includes files for projects funded by Sloan Foundation grant
    - NYU: Miscellaneous Materials, 1979-2007; 5 folders (Box 31)
      Includes documents for routine department business and faculty interaction with university administration
    - NYU: Remarque Institute, 2010 (Box 31)
      Includes files for routine business
    - NYU: Report to Dean, 1986 (Box 31)
      Draft report on external recognition of faculty achievements
    - NYU: School of Education, 2002 (Box 10)
      Includes files related to potential projects with the School of Education
    - NYU: Sloan Applicants, 1979-1981 (Box 10)
      Includes files for funding projects
    - NYU: Sloan Seminar, 1978-1982 (Box 10)
      Includes files for seminar series sponsored by the Sloan Foundation
    - NYU: Sponsored Research Training Manual, 1984 (Box 10)
      Includes files on sponsored research projects
    - NYU: Stern School of Business, 2010-2012 (Box 10)
      Includes files for routine events and business at the business school
    - NYU: Subcommittee on graduate education, 1983 (Box 10)
      Includes files for committee service
    - NYU: Teaching and Department Duties, 1983-1986; 13 text files; less than 1 MB. (Digital-materials RL00092-SET-0002, Disk RL00092-FL5-0107)
    - NYU: Tenure and Promotions, 1977-1983 (Box 10)
      Includes files related to faculty reviews
    - NYU: Thijs ten Raa, 1981-1985 (Box 10)
      Includes files related to hosting visiting professor
    - Princeton University, 1952-2012; 4 folders (Box 10)
      Includes files for routine department business and appointment renewals
    - Princeton: Rutgers Review Committee, 1983 (Box 10)
    - Recommendations, 1975-1989; 11 folders (Box 10)
      Includes letters of recommendation written by Baumol and received from others
- Personal, 1928-2013 and undated
  Contains biographical materials, photographs, other personal documents, and samples of Baumol's original artwork. Of note are Baumol's sketchbooks and two canvas paintings.
  - Addresses, undated (Box 82)
    Includes materials for keeping track of addresses
  - Addresses, 1988-1998 (Box 27)
    Includes documents pertaining to addresses of contacts
  - Administrative Matters, 1982-2007 (Box 27)
    Includes personal documents pertaining to salary and retirement
  - Art Contests, 2007-2008 (Box 82)
    Includes materials and artwork for contests
  - Art Show, undated (Box 82)
    Includes artwork and photographs for an unnamed art show
  - Articles about Baumol, 2002-2006 (Box 27)
    Includes copies of magazine articles and other writings about Baumol
  - Awards, 1989 (Box 27)
    Includes publishing award from MIT Press
  - Baumol as Artist, 1957; 1981-1982; undated (Box 82)
    Includes show programs, newspaper clippings, and articles related to Baumol's artwork
  - Baumol as Student, 1928; undated; 4 items (Box 82)
    Includes notebooks from classes taken by Baumol
  - Baumol Biographical, 1976-2006; 9 folders (Box 27)
    Includes newspaper clippings and other materials documenting Baumol's life and achievements
  - Beans, Curd, Fresh etc, undated (Box 82)
    Includes recipes
  - Bibliography, 1989 (Box 82)
    Bibliography of Baumol's publications
  - Biographical Statement, 1988 (Box 82)
  - Broadcast of November 13, 1991 (Box 43, Audio-cassette RL-00092-CS-0001)
  - Calendars, 1976-1978 (Box 82)
    Calendars of economists' birthdays
  - Cards, undated (Box 82)
    Includes personal cards received
  - Cards and Notes, undated (Box 82)
    Includes various business cards and unsorted notes
  - Chapter on Baumol's Contributions, 1996 (Box 27)
    Includes copy of book chapter by Elizabeth Bailey and Robert Willig on Baumol's contributions to economics
  - Corel Painter, 2003 (Box 82)
    Includes notes and instructions on using the Corel software
  - Curriculum Vitae (CV), 1970-1987 (Box 82)
  - CV electronic records, undated; 5 text files; less than 1 MB. (Digital-materials RL00092-SET-0001, Disk RL00092-FL5-0006)
  - CV electronic records, 1990; 5 unidentified files; less than 1 MB. (Digital-materials RL00092-SET-0001, Disk RL00092-FL5-0001)
  - CV electronic records, 1980-1988; 112 files (post script and unidentified formats); less than 1 MB. (Digital-materials RL00092-SET-0001, Disk RL00092-FL5-0020)
  - CV electronic records, 1987; 8 text files; less than 1 MB. (Digital-materials RL00092-SET-0001, Disk RL00092-FL5-0056)
  - CV electronic records, 1983-1987; 19 text files; less than 1 MB. (Digital-materials RL00092-SET-0001, Disk RL00092-FL5-0115)
  - Drawings, 2006; undated (Box 83)
    Includes various drawings by Baumol related to holiday cards and catalog artwork
  - Facsimile of Signature, undated (Box 27)
  - Financial Items, 1985 (Box 27)
    Includes minor bills and receipts
  - History of Entrepreneurship Lunch Session, 2006 (Box 43, Audio-cassette RL-00092-CS-0002)
  - Holiday Cards, undated (Box 82)
    Includes homemade holiday cards from William and Hilda Baumol featuring Baumol's artwork
  - Institutional Investor, 1979 (Box 82)
    Includes clippings from Institutional Investor magazine
  - London, Meyer, undated (Box 82)
    Includes copies of newspaper clippings
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 27)
    Includes unlabeled personal notes and papers
  - Miscellaneous Photos, undated (Box 27)
    Includes printouts of digital photos
  - Museum of Money, 2002 (Box 27)
    Includes documents related to founding of the museum of money
  - Natal Horoscope, 2003 (Box 27)
    Includes a horoscope for Baumol
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1991-2012 (Box 82)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 2002 (Box 27)
    Includes newspaper clippings about Baumol's work
  - Notes, undated (Box 82)
    Includes unlabeled hand-written notes
  - Notes, undated (Box 27)
    Includes unlabeled personal notes
  - On My Sculptures of Carved Wood, 1981 (Box 82)
  - Painting 1, 1973 (Oversize-folder 1)
    Abstract canvas painting by Baumol
  - Painting 2, 1980 (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Personal File, 1989-2008 (Box 27)
    Includes various notes and personal items
  - Personal Files, 2007-2013 (Box 82)
    Includes files related to personal matters
  - Personal files, 1983-1988; 58 document and text files; less than 1 MB. (Digital-materials RL00092-SET-0001, Disk RL00092-FL5-0051)
  - Photos, undated (Box 82)
    Includes unlabeled personal photographs
  - Profile Photos, undated (Box 82)
    Includes official photos for use on academic webpages and publications
  - Publication List, 1947-1987 (Box 82)
  - Publications lists, 1988; 5 document files; less than 1 MB (Digital-materials RL00092-SET-0001, Disk RL00092-FL5-0003)
  - Publications lists, 1988; 5 text files; less than 1 MB. (Digital-materials RL00092-SET-0001, Disk RL00092-FL5-0005)
  - Publishing Contracts, 1969-1970 (Box 27)
    Includes copies of publishing contracts
  - Recipes, undated; 4 folders (Box 82)
    Includes various recipes
  - Red Queen Game, 1997 (Box 82)
    Includes copy of description of the game
  - Sculpture Pictures, 1973-2001; undated; 3 folders (Box 82)
    Includes pictures of Baumol's sculptures and related materials
  - Shores, 2011 (Box 82)
    Includes documents from a homeowner's association
  - Sketchbooks, undated; 3 folders (Box 82)
    Includes small sketchbooks containing various artwork by Baumol
  - Sketchbooks, undated; 5 folders (Box 83)
    Includes large sketchbooks containing various artwork by Baumol
  - Sketches, 2011; undated; 3 folders (Box 83)
    Includes sketches by Baumol
  - Sketches, undated; 7 folders (Box 27)
    Includes sketches in various formats by Baumol
  - Travel, 2007-2012 (Box 82)
    Includes files related to personal travel
  - Unlabeled recording, undated (Box 43, Item RL-00092-RR-0001)
  - Watches, 1984-2006 (Box 82)
    Includes materials and photographs related to Baumol's interest in watches and clocks
  - Watercolors, 1991; undated; 3 folders (Box 83)
    Includes small watercolor paintings by Baumol
  - Wine, 2005-2010 (Box 82)
    Includes labels from wine bottles and related newspaper clippings
- Audiovisual materials, 1978-2006 and undated
  Conditions Governing Access
  [Original audiovisual materials and electronic records media are closed to use. Use of these materials may require production of listening or viewing copies. Please contact Research Services before coming to use this collection.]
  - Reel-to-reel audiotape: Velocidad Grabación-3 3/4, miércoles 11 de enero de 1978 [1978 Jan 11 Wed.], 15 minutos del día 12 Lado 2 [15 minutes of day 12, side 2] (Box 43)
  - Audiocassette: History of Entrepreneurship, 2006 Oct. 20-21 (Box 43)
  - Audiocassette: Broadcast of Nov. 13, 1991 (Box 43)
- Unprocessed additions
  Access restricted: Original audiovisual materials and original electronic media are closed to use. Use of these materials may require production of listening or viewing copies. Please contact Research Services before coming to use this collection.
  Access restricted; unprocessed additions require additional arrangement, description, and/or screening. Contact research services for more information.
  - Accession 2020-0078 (3 linear ft.) (Box 87, Box 88)
    Addition includes professional files in paper format and electronic media.